Oh welcome to voices with verve a key
I'm joined by a good friend of mine
Taylor
Barrett and Taylor actually facilitates
the circling group that attendees one of
the two facilitators he and his wife
Johanna and so Taylor's also doing some
really interesting work around circling
authentic lading and also he's in an
interesting way he's taken up the call
of trying to bring a little bit more of
the feel around me a term philosophy ax
into circling and what does that look
like and so I'm just going to turn it
over not to tell her to to introduce
himself and talk a little bit where he's
coming from and what he what he's
seeking for mm-hmm yeah thanks John
yeah so I think I've been I've been
working in authentic relating for the
last seven years was not something I was
looking for my wife had found it and we
weren't married at the time we had only
been dating for like two weeks and so he
sort of said like hey you wanna you know
try this thing and I was just in a
position where I was really hoping to do
two new new things so I did this thing
and I I had no idea like the end result
of is I had no idea that I needed this I
had like I had no concept of what was
possible like I had never done you need
therapy I had never done any sort of
group process work like I was just very
much an automatic mood was my life and
it was amazing after our first event we
spent hours sort of debriefing it and
immediately changed our language changed
the way we were relating to each other
and we just started burning through you
know like our first stuff you know like
our material yeah I'm just getting more
intimate and more you know clothes and
like getting down to the heart of the
real truth what was underneath you know
all our behaviors all our surface
behaviors right so I mean the
the magic of that experience and sort of
being on this rocket ship together had
us like do all the events and then then
the retraining is being offered so we
took the trainings I'm just really so
believing in what this could do for us
so um so yeah we took over the Toronto
community about four and a half five
years ago and started building it out
adding more events and more facilitators
and training them so that's sort of how
that's been going
but I mean all this work you know this
authentic relating work is really falls
under sort of an umbrella of relational
leadership or more maybe more
immaculately relational self leadership
and then how do we bring ourselves and
how do we take responsibility for
ourselves in relationship with other
people and the frame for this is around
authenticity and the way we hold
authenticity is it's um it's more where
our outward expression more accurately
reflects our inner experience and this
is a little bit different than say like
a radical honesty practice we just share
everything that comes in your mind right
here this is sort of in service of
something right so you know for example
if I was upset with you and I I decided
you were some excluded name you know in
Frederica honesty I might just say that
thing a little bigger
and I think of relating I also might say
that thing but probably more accurately
it's just like you know like I noticed
when like feeling really angry with you
you know and then when we get really
good at it we might notice something
that's underneath it like and that's
because I'm feeling a bit hurt that
about that thing that you said you know
so we start to sort of own our
experience not make you responsible for
make other people responsible for we
sort of like take it back and sort of
own it it's almost like a subtle shadow
integration and that motion of sort of
taking it back from you identifying the
right right yeah so that's um that's
sort of the you know the basis for me or
the way I fold authentically
and can be sort of looked at as um as a
way of being like a way to be in the
world you know live through this
relational self leadership but then
there's things that are known as
authentic relating practice which you've
experienced and sort of the warm-ups
that we do yes yes yeah and we sort of
liken those to like going to be
emotional workout gym you know so when
you go to the normal gym you know you go
do squats over here and you go do a leg
press over there and you do bicep sear
and an authentic relating practice we
might work on our empathy we might work
on our listening skills you might work
on noticing like bringing language to
our emotions and so that's so the
pathetically can practice and encircling
which I know you're familiar with but
you know it's this we call it an
intersubjective meditation practice it's
like a group practice there's different
formats of it and slight variations to
it but this also fall I consider this
falling under authentic relating
practice to me it's like the marathon
you know we go to the gym so that we can
run the marathon into me circling the
sort of yeah yeah so and so that's you
know what would I've been up to for the
last seven years and then I noticed
about six months ago or so after
watching a number of your episodes of
awakening from the meaning crisis or and
some of the stuff that Peter was doing
like you know he was really like shaking
sort of containers yeah Peter limber
yeah yeah like sort of shaking up
containers and sort of like clashing you
know like Darren tech groups and sex and
I just noticed like through that I think
you said he would started talking with
maybe Jordan Hall at that time and gonna
sing stock and I noticed rebel wisdom
and was starting to talk with with you
know and I'm watching these videos and
I'm like I'm starting to get this sense
like oh yeah there's something here like
we were sort of like six months ago it
seemed like we were sort of teasing
around the emergence of some idea where
as something that to me was a bit
transcendent of circle
right right they'll love circling I'm
still gonna do circles from the train
circling I think it's critical and the
intention that we bring encircling
to really like be with you in your world
as beautiful as it is is transformative
of a practice as it can be it also has
some limitations and you know by trade
I'm a problem-solver you know before I
got into this I wrote software I'm a
software engineer right so my brain
actually works really well for you know
solving problems and and then you're
bringing in this frame of sense making
while I'm like feeling really integrated
with the circle I'm like oh what can we
do with this right right at the same
time I'm thinking about this I'm like
sitting in one of your q and A's and you
say oh what if we take circling like
drop a problem into it okay we're
talking about very similar things here
yeah that's when I had contacted you
said I can't answer to think about you
know running a project to try to blend
the first second and third person
perspectives into a more whole
discussion right right right
because in my sense was circling we
focused primarily on the eye and week we
had a very first and second person we
don't talk about a lot of content there
I've known people in this community for
five years I have no idea to what they
do for a job you know like that is not
the way that we actually interact um but
when it comes to like the world's
problems I'm like oh my god I just see
problems everywhere that's just my
organization really it's a bit of a pain
but it's a bit of a department too
so you know pre Kovan pre-pandemic the
biggest pain that I was experiencing in
my circles is sort of like ideological
possession and polarities you know right
like they're happening in society and
just as clashing and it's just like wow
why can't you know mmm this this sucks
so uncomfortable and terrible and I I
can from one side see it as like
necessarily developmental stage for
people to go through for society to go
through and it's like surely we can do
this better so that was sort of the fie
that is sort of lit me up and sort of
experimenting with trying to find a
different way to have a conversation
around polarities what sense happened
since the pandemic has come is somehow
that didn't feel so salient anymore I
was like okay I mean that's still out
there but I want to have a different
kind of conversation and I want to have
much more of a collective intelligence
style conversation and that's been the
last few rounds if the experiment have
really been not so much about the way in
which we are saying but trying to bring
our relationship to the pandemic into
coherence in the hopes that it might
start to reveal some really strong
insight or even internal motivation and
to turn around and start moving into
action right that's sort of been the
trajectory of it for me so there's a lot
there wow that was great
no no no don't apologize that that's why
I didn't interrupt it was it was
unfolding really really was very smooth
intelligibility so that obviously means
that there's some ways in which you put
your finger on a couple points but I
want you to go back and just unpack if
you would please a little bit more about
you know why is circling inadequate for
the things you're pursuing here no and
yeah and I will of course the caveat the
acknowledgement you love circling it's
part of your way of life I get that
that's not what I'm asking I'm asking
you for the I'm asking you for critique
not just criticism yeah yeah for sure
yeah so I think my perception of
circling although I might practice
circling a little bit different than
I've always had a bit of an allowance
but there's a tendency within circling
of this sort of intention to to go
really inward get into do a subjective
and to explore the subjective and while
I think our subjective relationship
with whatever the third person problem
is per se is extremely important we
don't tend to actually look at the
problem the problem tends to be
something like oh I'm really hard on
myself or I feel a lot of fear about
being alone during the pandemic right
and that you know might be you know an
exploration of you know well you know
what does that fear work where does it
live in your body what does that feel
like all very helpful and important
explorations right but I think you sort
of said something about this before -
it's sort of like ok but now - now what
do you do with that you know like where
do you go from there so I think it
affords great personal insight and and I
see it as a fantastic personal growth
tool but as I considered this this sort
of this shift out or I've been seeing it
as a bit more of a I think you'd call it
in a Gaga you know sort of arise is that
that's that's still there we still had
some some degree of insight into into
our subjective but it also like seems to
like bring something forward into the
space that men others can sort of play
with and then form their relationships
to it you know and we can sometimes do
that and circling but again it comes
right back to the individual and the eye
and the subjective like oh it's a little
bit different for me and again very
important distinctions but we just tend
to devalue the it the the thing we don't
come in with a problem we might talk
about how we relate to the problem but
we don't it doesn't afford much wisdom
self wisdom sure but like collective
wisdom and right bless certain yeah so
there's a way in which if you'll see
this resonates you know that certainly
the sort of really activates actualizes
you know collective intelligence and
even puts it into this
you know dynamic flow and and and people
do note that they note that you know you
we often get into you know - people will
resonate and they'll do that subjective
exploration facilitating each other but
we we've noted in circling that but
there's there's there's ways in which
the circle sort of weaves these things
together and does can sometimes disclose
something beyond the individual right so
and when I and I remember there was one
thing we were did where it was actually
an introduction that you and I had at
the end of a circling where the the
shift in the locus of intimacy was off
you and I being intimate with each other
that wasn't that wasn't abandoned but
that was back rounded and that
platformed an intimacy with the process
of intelligibility itself with the sense
making process itself and so and that to
me was a bit of a felt shift and so
there's a possibility that once we
activate it and actualize it we could we
could couple to it we could we could we
could like sail on the wave of intimacy
if you don't owe me some metaphors here
Jordan halls metaphor right with a kind
of direction and orientation like so
that you know like you said we could we
could drop a problem in or we can drop a
mystery in microwave and and again not
to foreclose that we're getting looking
for an answer I think of it more as
could we activate collective
intelligence and shape it into
collective wisdom so that we get into
right relationship with reality and the
problem just like circling brings us
into right relationship with each other
people are invoking that language a lot
I feel so connected and it's so good and
it's so right right it hasn't finished
our relationship we don't go well you
know Taylor that was it that now we're
done right right so instead we're coming
into right relationship but we can that
what we there are things there are
things and I'm using this term as
neutrally as possible there are things
we have to come into right relationship
other than with ourselves and just each
other we have to come into relationship
with ways of being with patterns in our
culture with the unfolding of reality
itself and
Cobin crisis makes that deeply apparent
to us is that does that land with you oh
yeah totally totally I almost see it is
like the the circling part of the
process that you and I are exploring
like um sets us up not so much to
achieve this end goal but it sets us up
in such a way in which it's possible
that something could actually manage
it's almost like without that intimacy
you know there there isn't a trust I
might not be willing to try out a new
idea or you know bounce that off because
you know all maybe normally I don't know
who you are you're going to judge me but
here it's like over relationship from
work we're getting each other and we're
reciprocally sort of building this thing
it affords yet for it some a lot more
trust and therefore I think freedom of
exploration is probably the way I would
I would look at it hmm
so that then so to quite sort of a
two-part question and let me let me give
some context realization for it you know
I mean I've been doing stuff with and
you mentioned it with guy and Chris you
know guy send Star Christmas with Pietro
Jordan Hall and other people about you
know trying to bring philosophy ax into
into circling guy calls it circling 2.0
but people are now sort of adopting the
term that Chris and I of the deal logos
because we're all so harkening back to
sort of the Socratic platonic template
of these kinds of open-ended discussions
right and that in which people are
getting they're accessing collective
intelligence but they're trying to
participate it such that it is turned
towards getting into deeper and more
comprehensive right relationships to
being to others to important social
ideals like justice and so the two-part
question is what is it specifically
you're trying to do in your experiments
we're talking like lay it out and and
the progression what are you finding
what have you learned
I mean I mean a good experiment should
always show
was challenge you it should be well some
of the predictions came it's a good
experiment if you say some of the
predictions came true and some of them
didn't and the ones that didn't give me
a better way of interpreting the ones
that did so that and then so your your
what you're doing and then how because
you know I've talked about it how is it
convergent with and how can it be put
into conversation sorry for the pun with
the sort of the dialectic dialogic to be
a dialogue owes project that I've been
involved in hmm yeah is that okay he's a
questioner was that too much uh I think
I get it okay correct me if I'm if I go
off into the weeds or something so yeah
the first the first couple of rounds
around it I had like it's focused on
people taking a side and putting four
people into a conversation a facilitated
conversation and then I had people on
the outside observing that conversation
and there were a few reasons for doing
that but I wanted some people just in an
observational third-person role to
create a bit of an arm's length distance
to when we started actually talking
about the content and what I found in
that was rather I mean there could be a
few reasons of why it it sort of worked
and sort of didn't work so we picked a
topic and this topic was about the
change of lyrics around the baby it's
cold outside
it was miss time because it was it was
about right for the time and there were
people who said like that was ridiculous
they shouldn't change the lyrics and
keep like we tried to pick something a
little on the safe and just to try out
the structure first like really and and
you know what happened was you know for
me as a facilitator I started off into
it
I started off from the third person and
just sort of like checking in with
everybody to see what their position was
and get shared reality about that
position fortunately what happened is
the the people in the conversation
actually found their own points of the
meeting and started to come a little bit
more into an eye are we around this idea
so we could sense the potential that
something about it didn't feel as
intimate or se as potent as say
if we circled around really one with a
circling intention and then the next
time I did it you know we really
struggled again like it was something
about maybe it was the sample group you
know taking people who are familiar with
owning their experiences and you know
really not projecting and and being able
to see complexity and not actually
really take a full-on you know hard
stance on a particular position that
seemed to be really difficult just to
tease out the polarity to even do the
experiment so in some ways with that a
bit fizzled it made it really sort of
this walky discussion and like well how
are we gonna like come to some meeting
point of understanding somewhere in the
middle of shared reality around these
issues just it just wasn't really not
happening so then I tried a couple more
rounds but you know this was now into
the pandemic and I was noticing the way
people were relating to this particular
issue I was trying to have other
discussions about the pandemic and I
noticed every time I would try to talk
about the it of the pandemic it was so
hard to come into any kind of coherence
because everybody had their unique
personal impact of how they were being
impacted by the pandemic it was only
until we could actually address and have
them bring their voices forward and feel
heard and seen and how they're impacted
did they seem open or even capable of
starting to take in some of the
objective aspects of it so that was like
okay I definitely need to come with you
know was the first-person perspective
first so that was very important to sort
of learn but even in that particular one
there were a number of gaps in capacity
in terms of relational capacity so there
was actually some pretty big gaps in how
people were relating to each other and
then to have like six people and about
an hour and like to try to get everybody
to sort of meet and it just wasn't
working so it further revealed to me how
important capacity is or at least some
sort of pedagogical
lead up to a contact setting in terms of
actually being able to do this really
well so you know you had mentioned that
one that one situation with you and I at
the end of circling where we said like
oh let's experiment with this and when
you feel like we're at the point let's
see zoom zoom out and then zoom in and
zoom out you know and I think that
worked so easily because of one you and
I already had whatever the relationship
was there was already that intimacy
already started encircling but then
there's a certain capacity of me to like
like I don't have any belonging needs
with you or with the group
I'm not afraid that you're gonna judge
me I don't have this other thread that I
asked it so it allows me to open up and
surrender to the the the symbolism that
was happening in that particular
exploration so on I'm noticing these
sort of these bits and pieces of wood
are the ingredients for success and and
how does even you know I hold a large
developmental lens when I'm working with
people and it's like we're like what can
we reasonably expect or how can we
configure this such that it's more
accessible I think I watch you and guy
and and Jordan do it the Ilocos
conversation and it's like yeah like
that makes sense
I would not would not be able to have
had that conversation with with the mix
a group that I have and there's you know
various reasons for that so it's
starting to sort of notice like how can
we bring this this relational leadership
style of conversation in which we can
actually work on a problem in a way
that's accessible to people that
provides like a leg up towards I think
you know more of a deal logos
conversation yeah so that's kind of what
I've been noticing in a real general
sense and trying to move towards that so
I'm imagining future ones might be you
know you might start to pick out a
specific invite group and set a specific
type of context of for people who I
think could really open their
perspectives in a very full
chuckle sort of theoretical perspective
and then see what happens from that
using the same tools I would say or the
same intention of you know let's let's
connect let's you know solve whatever
interpersonal thing to get the flow
going and then let's notice where are
the moments where we have it's the word
salience or sort of a cohesion around
something and then it's like okay now we
can pop out and now we can start to
sense make on it yeah yeah yeah so yeah
I'm trying to reverse engineer that - I
think you some documents around that so
so there's that and that's you know and
it's very much a work in progress so a
couple things come to mind
one one one is you know Peter and I are
talking about this you know sort of a a
progressive program of pedagogy like you
may be like you know maybe just art
we're just you know social noting and
then perhaps move into something like
empathy circling because Edwin argues
it's a great gateway practice right for
moving people from adversarial
winner-take-all into weight we can
actually make stuff together
we can write we can we can get into
right relationship with each other and
that that's much more important than
having the right view right relationship
right and then and then maybe taking it
into circling and then I've been tried
what would you do to like you said to
notice the moments where you people are
sensing the hand of the logos and you'd
get that zoom in zoom out thing
happening yeah so I think part of what
I'm saying is and I you did you did
bring a pedagogy
it sounds like ways in which we can try
and do the bridging and the capacity
affordance is if we have that
pedagogical program and you know it's
like when I'm teaching the meditation
course I don't teach people progr at the
beginning yeah you you have this
progressive build up of skills and
practices that scaffold people in so
that would be sort of the bottom up but
I also think um and you know and Kristin
I was talking about this and I wanted
I want to get your feedback on it that
that should be complemented with a lot
of sorry this is I know I'm struggling
for an adjective here I want to say the
sort of high level and that sounds
elitist
so I'm trying not to so high level via
logos that were you know and and also
ask people to they don't get it but
imitate it hey play with it pretend
right because that's what kids do that's
what kids do until they pretend until
they can comprehend right and so the
idea of getting a practice where we say
look we're gonna show you this and
obviously not at the beginning but let's
say people are starting to move into
this pedagogical program you say well
let's watch some of these and you're not
gonna be able to do that that's fine and
don't worry let's get into serious play
trying to imitate it try to imitate it
as much as you get and I'm not holding
myself out as something I'm just saying
imitate imitate the deal logos or
wherever we can find it
I mean cuz that's what that's why soccer
that's why Plato wrote the dialogues
right initially we sort of came it and
I'm saying maybe we could have a
simultaneous strategy where we're doing
this you know pedagogical program where
we have sequences of practices that
scaffold people in bridge them in build
their capacity but also give them a lot
of role modeling and write and say okay
just just imitate this play pretend what
you know play and pretend and imitate
play and pretend and imitate but this
because this is how kids also you know
this is how they go through
developmental stages and I'm wondering
if you know if we got a pedagogical
program of practices and then we had
sort of ritualized imitation series play
you go into a church that's how they
scaffold people into Christianity and I
don't mean I don't mean any insult you
take them through a catechism you build
them up but you also do a lot of
imitating of Christ you do a lot of
imitating of Christ and imitating
appalled and right and imitating of Mose
you do all that you do both those
together so what do you think about that
is a proposal yeah yeah I mean what I
noticed in the last round when I ran it
is there was a moment where I felt like
I was in contact with the lowest and
like
is the thing so I brought it forward as
an invitation nobody took it up so I
wait and I'm like you know they said
whatever they want to say I brought it
back in as an invitation you know sir
like what is it about this thing that
has like you want to do this and you
want to do this and I want to do this
what is it and they just didn't seem to
quite know what to do with the
invitation right which you know is more
on me than on them but I know at the end
of that I felt like we really got
somewhere like at the end of it like
everybody was like no I really enjoyed
that I want to do this again let's do a
series of these and so in you know for
me the thing that I trust the most is
like what was my intention and then
what's the felt experience I have at the
end of it do I feel like you know I'm
moving towards that intention or am i
moving away from it and I think to a
certain degree you know just having that
discussion even though we didn't you
know go into some sort of you know huge
relevance realization around you know
why we have a tendency to give the
perfect device to other people but not
to not take it on herself
good you know which was the piece I
think all and you're going to that it
stays that oh but I think just the idea
that we can have that conversation start
bringing in that third person was a very
different type of conversation that I've
ever had with that group of people and
it and I canvassed them I asked them and
it was very different than any other
conversation that they had to so it's
almost like we're hinting at the
potential the more and more in which we
sort of exercise this so I I think even
just sort of the role-playing idea or
sort of the imitation idea I think would
also serve that in very much the same
way it creates a comfort with the
intention in the container of what we're
here to do and maybe I'm not going to
quite you know I'll need the training
wheels and then I'll take the training I
might fall over but you know I get an
idea of what it is that we're doing
because I've seen somebody ride a bike
before I've never seen somebody ride a
bike before I might look at the bike and
not know what in the heck I'm supposed
to do with that exactly that's a
beautiful analogy
yeah so that's all I say I think that's
I think that's a great idea
and I appreciate you bringing it forward
because it gives us an idea okay I know
what I'm gonna do
well I mean and this is also something I
guess I'm trying to argue for in an
exemplified you know I keep going back
to this template of dialectic and
Socrates and Plato and it keeps it keeps
being a fount of intelligibility it
keeps giving me because and there's and
you actually see because you actually
see it in the dialogues that people like
even the operatic dialogues the
dialogues where you know they bring up
some problem and they don't get a
solution and it's it looked at
argumentatively it was like well well
that was useless no we didn't figure out
what you know what courage is but it
like but if you pay attention to the
dialogues what happens is people get
educated right in a particular way they
they they they stop Trump they they say
they stop following the authority of
obvious Ness well you know just long
it's X right
or you know the authority of you know
sort of formal definitions well I read
that this is it right and and then what
happens right is as people get into that
and they instead get into the right
relationship with the logos what you see
is the people who like the people that
Socrates were was dialoguing with
they'll say things like well I want my
son's to hang around you hmm I want my
children to hang around you so although
you could also so although we didn't
come up with a definition of courage you
exemplified it you exemplified it you
know in a powerful way
you made it sort of beautifully
accessible to me and I want my son's to
stay around you because I think if they
could imitate you long enough then they
would get rights they at least get that
inkling you're talking about
and then that inkling gets linked to
them to imitation now of course they're
adults and so they have their egos and
they're not gonna imitate but they want
their kids their sons and this this is
very important in ancient Athens they
want their sons to start to
Socrates and I so I think there's
developmentally that modeling of the
relationship between inkling and
imitation is actually a very natural one
for us yeah and I think what I'm sort of
hoping I got I don't know ultimately
what we'll end up doing this
conversation if we just have the
conversation or if we find out like
actually people might actually want to
watch this conversation too and I think
that's why I had the observe and there's
a role two's I'm still trying to figure
out how to bring that back and I've
taken it out but something about it I
know feels right to me there's um
there's something I think really
valuable and having people in that
third-person role yeah Tom
my sense is is that through wasn't gonna
say through lose the thread now what was
the last thing I said was sort of Inc
inkling into imitation yeah yeah it was
note I know it's still on the threat of
imitation well the one thing that I
would say is when we when we train
people encircling before they know how
to be circle before we have given them
all the tools and I mean it's a highly
experienced real practice so really your
training is not done after we give you
you know the pedagogy anyways like I'm
gonna have to they do circling but at
first we won't call it circling we call
it something else so that you know the
pressure is there you know so we bring
in an element of circling and then we
start to say okay now we're gonna do it
this way you're just gonna circle me
like you know of course you know so we
start to sort of pad this out and grow
it so that they're technically always
have been circling but you know before
they have all the knowledge one may need
to tickle that structure so I think that
you know is already a thing that's in
place you're at least how I train people
in circling I'm and I'm pretty sure
others would too I don't think I'm sure
everybody's doing training circles so I
think that's very much a part of it you
know when you get the feedback which is
kind of what I was hoping to use the
observational GRU
or actually use this container also as a
training tool in of itself as a teaching
tool so there's the there's the insight
that it can afford and there's also the
practice of doing it and not being
successful as a teaching tool as well
yeah so I see what you're saying though
there's a sense in which the people in
the third person perspective maybe this
was the connection you were you were you
were feeling towards and they're going
from like you know participating in the
insight and the flow to seeing it as
something and when it works they are
getting something that they may want to
imitate they may want to participate in
it was that part of the intent of that
of having the group out there well I
certainly have gotten that when we would
go to take feedback from the third
everybody would start bringing in their
first persist objective sort of opinion
about the topic so I could really see
people you know who were in the third
person role really wanted to be a part
of that conversation
and that sort of validates the idea
right I think this was the thing I was
gonna say that maybe we can present this
as something that you know so you have
these fantastic conversations with
Jordan Hall maybe your your
conversations with him art of an
accurate analogy here or a frame maybe
take like a rebel wisdom one where David
Fuller's interviewing Jordan Hall or
yourself about something it's this sort
of discussion that's sort of in one
direction to the expert yeah you guys do
it beautifully but not everybody's an
expert so how do we bring people into
having a conversation like like you're
saying like it's not going to be this
but maybe we're imitating me what we're
building starting to build the capacity
through actually enacting the the
practice such that maybe it doesn't feel
like a bridge too far
oh well maybe I I'll actually share my
opinion this time oh actually now I'm
gonna stand for my opinion this time
well actually I'm gonna go do some
research on you know like um we're
giving them an opportunity that maybe
they feel like a sort of a
- I can do that as well rather than
watching you know beautiful and really
inspiring for me to our conversations
but it's just like they don't have a
bridge like how do I get to a place of
philosophy I write how do I do that well
maybe there's a practice here that
starts to crank that engine a little bit
that's good that's good I'm hoping for
no no that's good I like that so the the
thing that came to mind was a
pedagogical model of apprenticeship hmm
right and that and then yeah and you
don't you don't expose the apprentice to
to the master work at the beginning if
you that's what master piece comes from
this that's right right you you don't
expose them to perhaps masterpiece
conversations or well you don't forbid
them of course but maybe it's like you
said maybe what you need is you you need
sort of you need role models that are
also sort of timed quit that's you know
critical transition periods within the
pedagogical program so when you're like
when you're in this one here's a role
model that you can imitate for what to
do here and then when people move you go
oh here's a role model for what you do
here and then yeah here's a role model
for what you do there and then both the
bottom up we could do the enacting you
could also be doing the imitating and
that you could scaffold people up and
then when they get and then you say okay
now here and you present something like
that yeah totally yes yeah and that
totally fits with my intention and why I
was holding this particular frame for it
rather than you know this you know
philosophy ax or like still the logos is
available in our conversations but I'm
we're not having a philosophical or very
broad sort of conceptual sort of
discussion but I believe that the the
thing that we're doing the the motions
that we're doing the zooming in is you
know the integrating of these three
perspectives those are happening in both
of our explorations yeah yeah that's
good that's really good yeah well they
I'm glad I'm recording this because this
is going to be very valuable for the
work
doing so like I guess are you going to
continue the experimentation or is the
is the is kovat really putting a dent in
in in trying to keep things going no no
I'm actually we've done more fortunately
because of online it's a little bit in
plus people aren't as busy I guess yeah
so there are people are a little bit
more available but also because I've
shifted some of the experiment down to
smaller groups I you know I had over
complexified it I think I was trying to
like track way too many things in the
first couple rounds I'm like okay I need
to like distill this down into the
basics and then bring something that's
always how experimental design goes
that's always our experimental design
yeah I feel so much better here I
thought it was like why am i over
complicating this so no actually I'm
actually thinking about doing a series
that is massively influenced by the
experiment and not actually connecting
this series to the experiment but sort
of having maybe one of these entry level
style of discussions that starts to
bring in that first or second layer of
complexity and then if we can sort of if
that's working really well then bring in
you know bringing the added complexity
and then maybe we'll do one more app or
actually like zooming it like way out
and moving maybe into some idea of sort
of a philosophy or like really
conceptual thinking once we sort of
built up this relationship to the
practice so that's my loose plan for the
next couple of weeks is to to sort of
start a series of these conversations
that I think will will fit more into the
intention of the experiment that's cool
that's cool so yeah there was a couple
things that came up when you were you're
mentioning that so
what what what do you think about this
Pratt like you knew I was gonna ask this
this practice and I don't mean just
circling I mean the whole pedagogical
apprenticeship from you know from maybe
you know social noting up to full-blown
deal logos right and and the way it's
you know it's it's exemplifying a way of
being not just a way of thinking that's
part of what's behind the whole notion
of authentic relating how is that what
so what I want to use what I want to say
something like what relationship does it
have in affording a response to the
meeting crisis and what relationship
does it have with with responding
affording a response to the way the co
vid crisis is really exacerbating the
meeting crisis yeah so I'm really
excited and I'm like oh my god there's
so many like entry points into this
discussion what I would say because I'm
holding that developmental lens and I
just can't seem to let it go it just
seems to work so well for me and sort of
how I perceive and make sense of the
world and and relationships with other
people and what I really see is is that
you know if we look at the crisis of
meaning is you know I've sort of held to
this frame that you know we don't we
don't have this institution or this to
turn around and give our power away to
or to enter into community with like I
used to be the church writer or a
particular faith or religion and as that
sort of starts to die off in a sort of a
post truth world it's like what what is
the thing that is greater than our egos
greater than ourselves that we want to
give ourselves to like that seems to be
like a biological matter is mattering
exactly yeah belong to something bigger
than ourselves and we need to make we
need to feel like we're connected to it
in a way that matters to it yeah yeah
yeah exactly and and I think you know
through authentic relating the thing
that matters is the quote unquote other
which is in very very many ways also
ourselves right so I sort of hold a
particular frame that you know yes God
exists but it is exists within here
within my perception within my relevance
realization within my salience landscape
you know that's what's there and can I
can I open transcend my ego and allow
that information into guide so that's
sort of my spiritual orientation if we
were to call it right and I think my
experience like I didn't have that
before authentic relating so it was
through my experience inauthentic
relating of you know I went into
authentic relating as a misanthrope and
like people I really didn't like people
like I blamed everybody else for
everything that was wrong everywhere you
know I feel like I've got the capacity I
could love anybody and that came through
these practices of sort of being with
people in their world and noticing how
I'm impacted and then how they're
impacted by my sharing of it like it
created something richer in my
experience than it experienced anywhere
else so it felt like it was something
much greater than like oh there is
something here that I can't create on my
own I could sit here and meditate I'm
not gonna get this same experience that
I'm having in relationship with you or a
relationship with a group so that you
know just you know the enormity of that
and then how it brought value back into
my own perception of who I am and my own
identity and what I was able to learn
about myself just through the
reflections that would come back through
this like to me and it created a shared
context for me and my wife like it's in
so many ways it's become my world
and it I'd never thought about mission
and purpose until about a year into
doing this I you know there was a
weekend immersion so it's like really
intense like two three days of like just
you know dinner in her work and you know
looking in and relating and I just I got
I got so scared I got so scared because
I thought oh wow for me to do this thing
that I now feel called to do it's gonna
like blow up my entire life like my life
is going to change in this moment so I
just wanted to note and this is not you
know me this is not in any way an insult
I want to know a religious your language
is becoming feeling call they're
connected you're speaking of the logos
that you know this you know like it's
sacred to you it's transformative right
it puts you into right relationship with
yourself with other people I mean you're
so I sense if in we haven't talked too
much about you past together personally
but I sense that not only did you go
from being a misanthrope to being
philanthropic it sounds like you also
went from kind of a secular or
non-religious stance to a more spiritual
or religious in the sense of enacting
religio in the way we're talking about
here is that also something that
happened yeah totally yeah that's
exactly that's the way in which it is a
deep response to the meaning crisis I
mean it'll allow me and I if you feel
this as an imposition challenge me right
away but it seems to me this is kind of
like what I'm trying to talk about the
religion that's not a religion we are
activating and enacting the logos we're
feeling called about it we're in faith
to it we're just a dynamically coupled
it's putting us in the right
relationship with ourselves with being
with each other it's leading us to
aspire it's giving us mission all this
kind of stuff yeah you're not being
bound to particular you know Dogma dog
my set of propositions that Dogma that
emerges is purely reflective practical
its pragmatic dogma it's well the things
that are most are reliably in very
that afford us getting into this flow
that seems to me and I've noticed that
that's that's I mean in the circling and
reading about it that this spontaneous
emergence of you know of spiritual and
religious language that seems to be like
a common feature in the Indies in the in
in circling events and things like I've
seen well I've seen it in person and
I've read about it and it just happened
here between you and I when you were
relating oh it's so go ahead go ahead I
think it's fair to say that my my
language in general around any of these
newer experiences is very limited
because I really didn't have you know a
religious background I really didn't
have like this is a whole new world you
know like we make a joke it's like
seeing the matrix right right I think
that my pill and now you can't unsee
everything that you can now see yeah
through that it's like I don't have I
don't have your education and your mass
vocabulary too so for me it's like I'm
picking up and if this is the way in
which I'm imitating you know the people
who taught me or who are mentoring me in
it it's like these are this is the
language that they're using and I make
meaning using those words right so when
I read like your papers I have to like I
have to translate them on cuz I'm I know
what you're saying like oh this is you
know this is this thing in my world or
you know in my language exactly we're
time with the same thing but it's just a
language is different so I don't I think
that's more I'm not quite sure where
that comes from I don't I don't know
that I can identify that it's some part
of me that wants to identify with that
idea of spirituality or religion but
there is this perspective that I'm
experiencing things that are bigger than
myself
greater than my ego and in that space it
seems to me most of the you know sort of
academic circles most of that language
is religious language yeah yeah very
much you all you did it you explicitly
did invoke God in your description and
you know it's it's it's it's it's it's
the subtle tone a'ti of being connected
to something larger than yourself
that calls you you also talk to that you
feel called by it
it like it's it seducing you it's
drawing you forth it's ecstatic it's you
know strong you beyond yourself right
and so there's something deeply
aspirational a transformative about it -
totally and so I think that's right I
think I think that the way in which the
the practice practice is exemplify a way
of being is the way in which this
responds to the meeting crisis I don't
think it's going to produce a set of
propositions where everybody goes oh yes
of course
I don't think it will either but but my
sense is what it is or what it's in
service of is a transition through to
the next stage of development yeah for
me I see it's helping you know hopefully
helping Society like I'm bringing in
complexity the work that I'm doing
brings in complexity to most people's
lives and awareness of themselves in
relationship um you know like most
people don't consider construct like
they're not even remotely construct
aware most people can't even take their
own perspective right they can't even
art they don't even know what that is so
I'm trying you know again through the
the developmental Theory lens I'm trying
to bring in this complexity and
something that really matters to people
in that tends to be their relationships
right know the studies all say you know
what was the most important thing before
you get to is your relationships like it
just seems to be the closest thing to
objective reality we can put our finger
on and therefore to to bring sort of
this this mode of development or moving
through to grease the wheels to add the
complexity to create the you know is
that one of the one of my teachers says
you know change happens either through
and by accident or through discourse and
it's like these practices make us more
accident-prone Mac setting up these
containers like give us an opportunity
to clash I think you have a you have a
map that you brought I remember
and that's sort of a thing like it you
know and then you can zoom out from it
and you can look at it again and then
you break the frame right yeah you can
zoom out and look at the frame you know
and so to me that's what we're doing
through authentic relating through
circling and so I see it as like in
service of sort of bringing us through
to the next development to level and
sort of pragmatically but also in terms
of meaning is just it's been so deeply
satisfying like like I don't need a
thing out there it's not a car car
doesn't make me satisfied a new coat
doesn't make me satisfied in the way in
which coming into deep connection with
myself and with others like it's it's
that meaning it's just exactly yeah and
then you know in terms of the Kovach
piece sort of the you know this series
of of conversations that I want to start
is I want what I sense is I've sort of
been holding this question that pandemic
you know is creating a pregnancy of
possibility there's potential yeah
Clarence exactly yeah we were on that
call talking about that and for me it's
like okay what do we want to give birth
to yeah but I was on a call my fifth
round and I remember somebody was sort
of like I've got like this energy but I
don't know what to do with it they don't
know how you bring it into action yeah
so I'm hoping that we can having a
collective intelligence conversation and
we'll find a threat of coherence and
that that will build and grow into some
sort of you know sub meaning or micro
meaning or is in alignment with their
own individual meeting even if they
can't identify that meaning it'll light
something up and then below goes and
then bring that into action and I'm
hoping that that is what these
conversations you know you were talking
about the campfire right it's like
that's what I want to do I just want to
be a little bit more intentional rather
than casually talk very much very much
yeah yeah so
I mean there's a sense in which you know
we're trying we're trying to sort of
what is it Neurath wrath you know that
you're on a raft and you're rebuilding
it as you're as you're as you're
floating on it and I think you know
we're trying to from within the culture
we're trying to rebuild it this is the
slogan I have about stealing the culture
right you know you know if we can make
ways of life and ways of being with
ourselves and with each other and with
the world like that do that what you
just described that sort of that
expanding field of coherence I mean I
think we could we could do what you know
what religions like Christianity and
Buddhism did it didn't go in and say you
know I think at times they did but
mostly what they did is they went in and
they gave people these new ways of
talking and being and seeing and growing
right and and then what happens is it
you know and a new culture emerges from
and I think that is there's a potential
for that now with the Kairos were in one
of the things you can see and you can
even ask people is was what are you
reflecting on now like that you weren't
reflecting on before all right like what
is what is coming to mind more what's
oppressing what's demanding and and and
and God has this wonderful phrase and I
like playing with it riffing on it I
think well you know coming to terms
which has both the sense of you know
coming to words articulation but also
confronting and you know you know not
trying to avoid any more thing
so a way I've been thinking about it
asking people is what's coming to terms
for you right now yeah I like that and
and again and and of course this will
and so there's there's a sense in which
the because we are out of normality and
we're not going to go back to more the
even Trudeau said were in this is the
new normal right
oh right because we're out of it we I
think we are now willing to reflect upon
meaning and intelligibility I get your
point we're not gonna many people can't
reflect on with great expertise and that
is not a criticism of them yeah oh right
and it shouldn't be taken like in in any
way as that but there's at least a
stance of reflection that is now I think
becoming more pervasive that wasn't
there a couple months ago yeah yeah
totally I mean not even I think to a
certain extent for some people I think
it was available maybe a couple you know
a few weeks ago but for a lot of people
it didn't seem like it was quite
available for them yet because there is
still no excuse me the whole situation
was so novel to them yeah it just had
you know and now as you you know my my
experience is you know as the novel
becomes integrated it becomes sort of
your background or it becomes you know
the water you're swimming in now you can
actually afford to to look at something
else yeah you know like other things
become salient to you now that you know
you've the low-grade anxiety of you know
what's gonna happen you know that's
that's still there but I mean your your
new normal is now more of a normal
you're not referring to it every day as
if you're normal it's just you know okay
I'm not going to work and I mean and not
not to in any way diminish you know
they're people who are suffering
biologically they're suffering
economically and and that is important
that is very important it's very
important but I also think that for the
for the people for whom the sort of the
the survival urgency is dropping they're
now facing like I said they're facing
meaning disruption normalcy disruption
and they're in a marathon now the sprint
of urgency is now giving way to the
marathon of endurance and and that
causes a different kind of problem
formulation a different way of relating
and I think that's what I mean where
people are coming into as a well Who am
I now
what am I supposed to do and we've been
trying to fill that with sort of
entertainment but it's not it's not
doing a very good job right and it's so
like well you know the Netflix is gonna
run out and you know all these shows
that are now being done from people's
homes rather than an in the studio is
that sort of funny and novel for a while
but it's it's getting kind of stale now
what do i do what do I do
terms yeah exactly exactly exactly yeah
no I completely agree and you know I
feel I feel I do feel privileged to be
able to actually consider this and have
these conversations very much in
survival mode and I get that so many
people are in survival mode and I you
know I have no expectation that you know
anybody can necessarily do that in that
place I mean it's for a reason why we're
not running training courses right now
it's just like it's this is not the
place for that kind of learning this is
a different kind of a learning that's
going to be happening here
so yeah they say you know don't don't
preach to somebody when they need a coat
exactly right that's not the thing you
know so I there's one more thing I
wanted to bring up and then I'll turn it
back you can answer that and then also
turn it back towards like giving you a
summative response to our conversation I
had a wonderful conversation with Tim
Madeline and Nora Bateson and Nora
Bateson and I with the collective we
very much want to talk again I bring
this up because you brought up the issue
about introducing complexity and that's
her thing the warm data is you know most
of our problems are complex problems in
which we are immersed we can't help we
can't sort of remove ourselves from them
and get the cold hard facts and of
course the co good thing right is very
much that kind of immersive complexity
right and you need the warm data and she
talks about that it's very important but
she's developed you know a distributed a
distributed cognition cycle technology
and she and I talked about it quite at
length and I noticed that it was
happening even in other meetups that
like in peter lindbergh stoah is you get
together as a group and then you break
up into small groups and the
return and when guy was taking us
through that we do that that's part of
the dictates of the medium right it's
also part of the dictates of human
conversation but Norris had this
brilliant insight where what she does is
and and for me I don't know she I don't
think she'd dislike this and we really
really really hit it off so I think
she'd at least find a soccer bug I think
she started a way of getting a virtual
Socrates into this because what she does
right is she
people going to the groups and then they
stay in groups for a while and then one
person moves between the groups and
people can move between the
conversations and what happens is they
come in and they introduce the other
groups perspective and that's disruptive
and then things get read and then what
you have is this dynamic small world
networks in which all the groups are
doing this distributed restructuring of
each other and then they come back into
the group and people have this there
they're there they have this much more
comprehensive perspective that they're
trying to bring in and I think that's
also something that we need to consider
as a you know as as one of these
bridging practices that helps to get so
rather than waiting for Socrates to show
up or hoping that everybody is in an axe
Artie I thought that's really neat
because what's happened is you've got
basically distributed Socrates and it's
happening dynamically and bottom-up and
and so I just wanted to hold that out to
you as a really interesting you know a
and I don't mean an insult by this to
you Nora but it's just really
interesting you know tweaking and
restructuring of this machinery that
actually affords again another way in
which we could sort of get people in
transition we can start to get them to
exemplify a much more complex system so
I thought that was actually really kind
of brilliant hmm yeah yeah I know I like
guys were talking about I noticed I got
you know pretty pretty lit up and
started smiling a lot there's something
and I think part of that's also you know
the motion that you're bringing to it
but it's also like yes you're talking
about complexity
and I really enjoy that and I also
noticed so boy seen as you were talking
about I wasn't even so much holding the
frame of complexity I was holding it as
like like a real practical exercise in
sort of for for the project or you know
for this you know this conversation that
I'm trying to have like how do you do
this in a large group how do you have a
large group conversation you know like
you know Peter on the stove
you know got like anywhere from 30 to 70
people coming on there you know you
can't have a conversation where
everybody's voice comes into the big
group with three to seven people but
with 30 to 70 people you have a lot of
cognition available yeah but if only
five people are talking a lot of it gets
wasted the collective intelligence will
get wasted and it might afford some
insight for those individuals and that'd
be great for them but you know it's the
group one missing out on it so just even
that that idea of like as being like a
stage to sort of like yeah determine
what is the thing that we're actually
going to discuss like almost canvassing
the collective around a broader topic it
it seems to me will come to a more
coherent and focused area then you know
almost like instead of us doing the move
when we're in you know sort of in the
eye we circling and then waiting for
that moment to come in small group it's
like oh can we bring in like a general
topic split everybody out have everybody
sort of in fact one another with with an
idea to see maybe something shifts in
that group or maybe they just dismiss it
and then we come back in and see like
okay so what's here for us now what
would like where are we now and maybe
that place allows us to turn around and
say okay this is the thing and then you
know if you've got a big group you can
either have that conversation because
you don't need all the voices in anymore
because you have some coherence or II
then you can break out and have that
specific conversation yeah so I noticed
I was getting really excited about that
and and also I think that's a training
tool for complexity yeah it is I think
it's also like a part warm-up as well
like that can be the warm-up to to turn
on in your life
more complexity of perspective and it's
interesting because the person the
people that are moving between the
groups and everybody will at some point
perhaps or maybe not they might just
stay but those people are really
embodying right they're not only they're
not only gonna be bringing ideas right
they're gonna be bringing timing and
pacing and perspective and a way of
inhabiting your body right and the
salience there all kinds of stuff is
gonna be carried between the subgroups
and and they're gonna start resonating
with each other in this really
interesting that's what she calls it a
warm data lab which i think is a really
cool idea um so like I said I think
what's emerging is like I said is this
very sophisticated pedagogical program
practices with some sort of with an
apprenticeship model with some you know
scaled imitation going on and where we
try to get people first to really
exemplify something and then get them to
reflect on it which so these are things
that are coming out so Taylor I wanted
to give you a chance to whatever you
would like to say that's you know
summative or on your mind as we sort of
bring this to a close
mm-hmm yeah just thank you appreciate it
you know it's like this was the
discussion that I think you and I were
going to have anyways yeah yeah and I'm
hopefully it's valuable for others who
are also playing in this field or maybe
feel inspired to play in this field too
because you know I think it was when
David Fuller was visiting Tron and we
said something about like we need to
fail and fail faster so I'm I'm all for
for throwing more irons into the fire
and the same of people are coming up
with and hopefully we can you know this
can start to come more into the field
because it was me hearing you know
schmuck Dan burger and wheel over here
and then you and Jordan Hall over here
and it's just like and then I'm having
my you know like there was a distributed
cognition happening just through you
know two videos yeah yeah it's like oh
if we can add a little bit more into
that you know other people trying
experimenting with cycle technologies
you know with sort of this intention to
move
Ward's you know philosophy a-- you know
to or to enact the logos through you
know through this sort of reciprocal
[Music]
engagement within a group or around a
problem i'm pretty excited about it
again I hold that frame like you know
and this frame primarily comes from
integral theory but it's this idea that
complexity is the lubricant that helps
us move through to the next stage yeah
I'm all for ways of making things more
complex but I want to try to find a way
to make them accessible to you know in
and have a practice it's only available
for people who've done your circling
training and everything else so I'm very
much on board and you know want to stay
in dialogue with you both sort of the
pedagogy like a how do we how do we do
this and how do we do it quickly
you know quickly and safely yeah yeah
yeah it has to be quick it has to be
safe it has to be scalable but it also
has to be rigorous so this all of these
is is the challenge we're facing yeah
well it's just been wonderful to see you
I haven't seen you for a while because
the our circles have been disrupted
though I've just enjoyed being in your
presence but I really I really this
really caught fire between us too as we
were as we were talking so I'm deeply
appreciative and I'm sure we will do
this again so I'd like to invite you to
come back you know let's go do some more
work and come back and you know let's
let's keep let's keep the progression
going totally yeah I love so great to
see you so great to talk to you
I hope it's sooner than later that we
get to see each other again me too
so thank you very much Taylor thanks
John take care